um great to be here with everybody
I'm just going to provide a 10 15 minute
up uh quick intro to what wev8 is and
because this is a hackathon I won't be
doing a lot of talking I'll just uh show
you code and show you what uh what you
can accomplish with bv8
so aviate is an open source Vector
database and a vector database I'm
assuming a lot of people know what this
is but I'll give a quick uh one minute
recap of this so a vector database like
we V8 essentially how it works is you
start off with your encoder models so
these are machine learning models that
any one of these companies like cohere
open AI hugging face host and create
you take these machine learning models
and you essentially pass your data
through these and this can be any
unstructured data right this can be text
images audio any type of data that you
can imagine you can pass through these
models and you take the vectors that
come out of these models the embeddings
and you can put them into a vector
database like
um and the reason why you would want to
do this is because now you have a
numerical representation of all your
data you can take a query you can
vectorize it through that exact same
model put it into a vector database and
then now you can do near object search
we don't the vector database will
understand what your data means it knows
how
close concepts are and then how how far
they are as well
and so classically this is the end of it
you can you can query your vector
database and you get a list of results
and you send that back to the user but
because this is DPAC and we're
interested in deep learning what I
thought I'd do is I'd put a spin on this
and really what we'd like to do instead
of outputting our results to users
is
we want to conduct Vector search in this
domain here
but we want to pass the output to a
large language Model A generative AI
model that can build on top of the
context that we've given it and so the
greatest application of this is in
generative search where I'm sure all of
you have heard about chat GPT
um so I'll demo how you can use weeviate
with chat GPT and the main idea behind
this is that chat CPT by itself cannot
be used on your own data so it's read
everything so it has a very uh a wide
general knowledge
but let's say you have proprietary
company documents or you have personal
documents track TPT doesn't know about
them it hasn't read it
what you can do is you can take all
those documents vectorize them and store
them into eviate if your documents are
not already vectorized then we have
separate modules that you can choose to
vectorize those put them into eviate and
then given a prompt that you would
usually give to chat GPT you can send
that prompt to ev8 and then we can
filter through those documents and give
you relevant documents and now along
with the prompt to chat TPT you can also
send these relevant documents so it can
add it can answer the question
grounded in the context of these
filtered documents right
and so this is how you get a customized
response out of chat GPT
um I know there might be a lot of
questions about the retrieval plugin the
retrieval plugin essentially gives you
the same functionality we're working
with openai to develop that as we speak
but for now for this hackathon uh we'll
make the generative module generative
openai module accessible to everybody
here so and and I'll demo that in just a
second so that you can work with leviate
and and chat GPT as well
okay so that's that's all the Talking
that I wanted to do I just wanted to go
over to uh to my code now and give you
guys a quick demo
all right so I put this demo together uh
last night and I wanted to demonstrate
the uh some of the most powerful
features of leviate here
I'm going to demonstrate the python vva
client but there we have a ton of other
clients that you can go to our website
and you can check out
um but the only thing you need to get
set up for this demo is the leviate
client so you can install that using
this and you want to make sure that
you're up to date with the with the most
recent client here
uh and uh to get a instance of V8 going
you can go to you can go to the WCS
Cloud you can make an account here and
you can create a free instance here uh
the only limitation is that you will
only be able to store a hundred thousand
objects but for a hackathon that should
be uh fairly good and and that'll be
online for 14 days and you can query as
much as you like
um for this particular demo we're going
to be using a model from a company
called cohere
and obviously we're going to be using
generative search so we need a open AP
openai API key
so I've created uh I've created a
leviate cluster here in preparation for
this for this demo
um some of the details here I've
uploaded a hundred thousand objects to
this cluster and these are just
Wikipedia articles so I took a very big
data set and I chunked off a hundred
thousand objects I put it into eviate
and I'll show you what we can accomplish
with this
so the very first thing I did here was I
created a database schema I specified
what I want to put into my database and
in this case because my data is already
vectorized I don't need leviate to
vectorize it for me if it wasn't
vectorized you could enable
vectorization and it would take a little
longer
but you would still be able to uh pop
the data in in a in a batch and then
vectorize as you go it's just quicker if
it's already vectorized
we create the database schema
and then this is the data set that we're
working with here and as you can see
it's just uh Wikipedia articles that are
chunked into paragraphs
and these are already we've already got
the embeddings the vectorization is
generated for us here
and this is a multilingual data set so I
think this uh particular data set has
over 50 different languages that you can
that you can use and this is one of the
reasons why we're using a cohere model
because it interprets multiple languages
as well
once you've got your data set loaded up
you can configure the batch operation so
you when you upload data to ev8 you it
batches it and then it uploads it in
batches so we're going to upload a
hundred data data points at a time
and then this is our uploading process
so I ran this so now I've got a hundred
thousand objects which is what my VBA
cloud service dashboard was showing
before
uh and then from this point on it's it's
mainly just about querying right so once
you've got this in this is a one-time
deal once you've got that data in now
you can query all you want so here I've
created a semantic search function
that I'll demonstrate in just a second
um I'm going to be demonstrating uh
keyword search so classical search I'm
going to do semantic search as well as
generative search but there's a lot of
other search modalities that we support
so you can do hybrid search where you
can combine semantic search as well as
classic word search
um
so if you want to learn more about that
all that information is available in the
documentation
so the most simplest search that we can
do here is we get we can look for the
word avocado and
here
oh one second live demo error let me
rerun this okay there we go
so here all it's doing is it's looking
for an article that has the word avocado
in it right so nothing special any any
uh database can do this
um where it gets interesting is when you
start to do semantic search right uh in
semantic search you can type in a a
query and it will return to you in this
case I've limited to five so it only
returns five articles the five most
relevant articles to this particular
search and it also gives you a measure
of distance between your query and the
article right so you can quantify how
similar uh a a returned article is
so this is fairly good I I didn't have
the word python in here but it returned
to me that the python is the most
popular machine learning language
because this is also multilingual and I
thought this would be a great
application specifically because
um we're in India you can ask it a
prompt in Hindi and so this is uh Hindi
for good movies and it will work just as
well because the model understands Hindi
it understands a lot of different
languages
so I think there's a lot a lot of
creative stuff that you can do with this
there's also so another example here you
can ask it for uh famous vacation spots
in Farsi and that works just as well
I'm a big Cricket fan and this is the
first talk that I'm giving in India so
uh there's no way that my demo wasn't
going to be about qriket so here I've
put together a bunch of examples of
generative search so the first thing I'm
going to do is look through a hundred
thousand Wikipedia documents and see uh
what it comes up with if I ask about
famous cricketers from India
so here you get some of the famous
cricketers you get multiple matches here
because the Wikipedia articles are
chunked into paragraphs okay
and so
uh and so oh that there's a question is
it using cosine based similarity yes
it's using well in this case it's using
the dot product actually
and then so here the metric that that
this particular model was trained to
optimize is the is the dot product
so this is semantic search what I refer
to in my um in my slides was you can
take a hundred thousand articles you can
pass in a prompt and then take the
filtered articles here so these five
filtered articles and you can pass them
off to chat GPT and you can ask it to
conduct or generate a output or answer a
task
taking these in as context and this is
where it gets really cool these are some
of the functionalities that chat GPT and
the retrieval plugin that they've
recently announced cater to as well
soon that is going to be available with
vv8 we're actually working on that right
now but uh for now what you can use is
the generative open AI module that we've
put together and it works in a similar
manner so let's break this down first
here
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
generate a prompt and this is the prompt
for chat CPT so this is what I'm going
to send to chat GPT
and then what I do is instead of sending
this directly to chat CPT through their
completions API
I'm going to query my Vector database
and I'm going to say give me all of the
titles and texts for articles that have
to do with famous cricketers from India
and I'm going to limit it to 3 and I'm
going to call this with generate single
prompt generate method on this what this
does is it takes each one of the three
documents that are returned from leviate
and it passes them to track GPT one at a
time so that it can answer this question
and now notice how I've embedded The
Returned Concepts within the documents
into the prompt so I can say write me
some interview questions I can ask
whatever the return title is and here's
some information about them
so if you run this prompt
takes a while because I'm using the uh
the openai API here
so here the first thing I want to point
out is that the relevant context here is
Virat Kohli so through the hundred
thousand documents when I search for
famous cricketers the very first one I
got was Virat Kohli and then what I said
here was write me some interview
questions that I can ask Virat Kohli and
here's some information about them and
this is their Wikipedia information
and it generated as a result of this
uh what questions you can ask him right
you can do a lot of other cool things
here as well right so you can ask take
those same three uh cricketers and write
me a heroic tale about them and you can
send a send a list of their
accomplishments
and here you get
so you get generated text about dravid
and a story about him
do the same thing about uh tendul's
guide
so this is one one returned response
goes to chat TPT you generate a you
answer a prompt with respect to that
context right the other way that you can
use degenerative search a generative
module is you can take everything that
your vector database returns wrap it up
and send it to chatgpt through one
prompt and so now it has to read through
everything that was returned so if you
return 10 articles it reads to
everything and it answers one question
it answers one prompt as a result of
that so this is the uh the grouped task
so here almost everything is the same
except now what I'm doing is with
generate I'm doing a group task and I'm
returning 15 articles 15 paragraphs and
it says here which of these cricketers
uh in these uh text is the most
accomplished and I wanted to choose at
least one
so here uh it shows me that these are
the different articles that it found uh
as a result of my search here Cricut
there's a lot of them are relevant there
are some irrelevant ones here as well
right so it returns some Cricket insect
ones as well
but uh once you take all these articles
and you pass them off to chat GPT it
prints out a list
great cricketers from those articles and
you can do a lot of prompt engineering
around this as well right so let's say I
do this exact same prompt but now I add
in uh choose at least one and explain
why not just the not just their names
but explain why they were chosen
and if you run this
it'll explain itself
so out of that list that we just saw uh
it picks Tendulkar and then it has a it
has a lot of context around why it's
picking to nuclear because we're passing
in the the text that the vector database
sent out
uh there's a question in the chat about
multi-tenancy if I have multiple users
clients on my platform should I create
separate indices for each of them or
should I store the user ID and leviate
and filter by user ID for every query uh
one second let me understand this
multiple users clients on my platform
separate indices for each of them
so you can you can choose to pass in
your own user IDs or you can pass the
unique objects in one by one and we can
generate the user IDs if you already
have the user IDs then you can pass them
in when you're passing your data into
ev8 so if you have a look at the quick
start guide on vva it'll show you
exactly how you can specify where your
user IDs would come from
and then if your data is not already
vectorized then you can specify exactly
how you want it to be vectorized as well
let's say you have multiple text fields
or you've got a text field along with
images you can use different modules
that we've already built in to eviate to
vectorize those let's say you have an
image as well as text
you can use the open clip module to uh
to vectorize both of those images and
text together what are some advantages
another question uh some advantages is
weviate have compared to vertex AI
matching engine Pine colon or any other
Vector Source uh yeah so I would say Eva
is completely open source the other
Advantage is that it's built on top of
approximate nearest neighbors search
hnsw technology
and I would say scalability is the
biggest power of weeviate we've tested
this Vector database with a billion data
objects and it scales
very well you can have a billion data
objects in fact the data set that we
tested on was uh from Facebook there's
fear data set and it scaled really well
the query time was very consistent from
a million to a billion objects right so
I think on a small scale uh there's not
that much difference but especially when
you scale scale up and when you want to
take an application into production
we've kind of battle tested this thing
specifically for that and I would say
that those are some of our major
strengths compared to Pinecone or vertex
AI
all right I love the questions you can
keep them coming by the way
okay so where were we on this
uh oh yes group task take all the
returned uh articles and send them to
chatgpt for it to answer a question
by the way these can these can all be
multilingual so the the model itself
does not need to be from open AI the
model itself can be your trained model
or from a third party it can be from
hugging face or cohere that doesn't
matter because it's the actual text
we're sending to chat CPT the it doesn't
care about the embeddings
yeah and this one uh were
we're asking it the same thing but now
we're we're crafting our prompt to be a
little better right so we've chosen not
just all the cricketers but just the the
best cricketers from India
and now it Compares against uh against
these
is streaming indices possible with vva
as I have data streaming in and I want
it to index on the flight does it take a
lot of time uh or indexing takes very
small time
yeah yeah so that's a great question you
can actually for that particular
application I would recommend you look
at this
so weviate has a spark connector
so if you've got data that's streaming
in from spark you can actually stream it
through spark directly to leviate and
it's very very quick so for that
particular application I would recommend
this
can this be used as a database to store
embeddings of a complete Enterprise for
Enterprise search
uh
complete embeddings for an Enterprise
I'm not sure what you mean by Enterprise
but if you mean your your own data
like uh for your for your company's data
for sure right that that's one of the
main applications right
um what you have to be what you have to
choose is how you vectorize that data
how you chunk it up
documents of the Enterprise yeah so if
it's a company proprietary document you
have to you have to be careful how you
chunk it up because how you chunk it up
will determine how you can search over
them
if you take entire documents and you
vectorize those entire documents the
vectorizations are not going to be
they're going to be centroids for those
entire documents so this is one of the
reasons why in the Wikipedia data set we
chunked up
individual paragraphs so but but that's
definitely an application of this you
can definitely take up take company
documents any documents really so if
you're running a legal firm let's say
you can take uh different documents
vectorize them put them into your
database and then you can do uh Vector
search over them
more concerned about the scale
yeah so uh how many uh what scale uh
vectors and how many objects do you guys
have
I can I can
answer more specifically if I know that
while you're while you're letting me
know let me let me finish this uh demo
off here
you can ask it a very interesting
questions here right so
you can ask it why all this text is
similar and you can give it
uh you can give it all cricketers and it
identifies this so this is not very
surprising the last thing here is I I
put in a bunch of uh cricketers here and
then I said tell me a story where all of
these people fight each other and I gave
it all the context of all the people
right so I gave them uh Wikipedia
Wikipedia paragraphs about all of them
and it generates a fairly good story
about how all of these different and
these are the characters of my story
that I got from wevie and I passed it to
chat TPT and it tells a fairly good
story about how
uh
how they can interact in a qriket match
oh okay so maybe 10 000 documents 10 000
documents is no problem
like I said um we V8 has been tested
with a billion documents uh so depending
on how you I should say a billion object
so the sphere data set has a billion uh
data objects if you take your 10 000
documents let's say you chunk it up and
you tokenize them or you uh you segment
it such that it turns into one million
documents you can easily search over
that store that into eviate
um the only uh the thing that might take
time is when you vectorize them right so
you want to make sure that you choose
the right vectorizer uh to vectorize
them and then once it's vectorized then
you can query query them very quickly
it's not a problem
another question let's say we want to
build a chat bot for follow-up q a
uh whereas the user replies context
changes what would be the best way to
approach that shall we vectorize and
index all possible conversations and
whenever a user asks a follow-up
question search for similar questions
and find corresponding reply given oh
this is this is pretty awesome so
just to answer that question we had a
recent blog that was was written up here
and it's interesting because this blog
answers exactly your question
the idea here is
if you want to create a chat bot
um you can't just uh you can't just ask
you can't just send individual questions
to chat CPT you have to send it the
context of previous questions and the
way you do that is by combining vv8 with
Lang chain and Lang chain allows you to
take the context of previous
conversations wrap it up put it into
your vector database and then send all
of that relevant information to uh to
chat CPT
and so let me show you an example of
this
so let's say you've got a conversation
going on with the chatbot
you can get you can take its answers put
it into eviate and then get it to uh
answer questions uh with regards to its
own previous answers
can you please point to the document
which mentions that you have tested with
one billion documents yes for sure so
that is another blog post here
so this is over here
if you look at
and we did this at the end of last year
let me just pull this up
so if you want to read
about the data set that we put in this
is the blog post that you want to read
that I wrote over here
so the sphere data set in vva and if you
want to know what type of hardware and
software we use to test the whole thing
there's a follow-up blog post here that
goes over uh everything and I can share
these links in the chat here for all of
you that are interested
so that's the one that covers the
metrics how how ev8 held up as we were
uploading data
uh so in in fact here we got up to 900
million objects and there was a linear
performance here
um as we were inserting the objects into
eviate and the data set is only as big
as this right and you can read more
about the
about the data set here and I will also
link the
the length chain where you can pass the
line chain blog post where you can pass
in uh context
all right uh
there's another question is there any
integration of
Lambda index GPT index with vv8 yes so
if you want to learn more about that
there's actually a Blog there's actually
a podcast that we recently did with the
founder of uh GPT index and that's on
our YouTube channel so you can you can
learn about that and you can also read
about it in our Docs
this is awesome
thanks everybody that's that's
everything that I had unless there's any
more questions
have fun with the hackathon and if you
make something cool with weeviate join
us on our slack Community share it with
us we always love to hear about it
all right thank you folks